<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<str name="umdm"><descMeta xml:lang="en"><mediaType type="text"><form>Poetry</form></mediaType><title type="main">Purgatory Lilt/ Statements by Circumstanced Me</title><agent type="creator" role="author"><persName>Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven</persName></agent><agent type="provider" role="publisher"><corpName>Tanya Clement</corpName></agent><covPlace><geogName type="continent">North America</geogName><geogName type="country">United States of America</geogName><geogName type="region">Maryland</geogName><geogName type="settlement">College Park</geogName></covPlace><covTime><century>2001-2100</century></covTime><culture>American</culture><language>en</language><physDesc><extent units="image">22</extent><extent units="line">116</extent><extent units="witness">13</extent></physDesc><relationships><relation type="requires"><description>First: Reel 5, Frames 299 and 300</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003087-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003088-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Second: Reel 5, Frame 301</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003089-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Third: Reel 5, Frame 302</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003090-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Fourth: Reel 5, Frames 303 to 305</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003093-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003092-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003091-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Fifth: Reel 5, Frames 306 and 307</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003095-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003094-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Sixth: Reel 5, Frames 308 to 309</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003097-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003096-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Seventh: Reel 5, Frames 310 and 311</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003099-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003098-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Eighth: Reel 5, Frames 312 to 314</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003102-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003101-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003100-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Ninth: Reel 5, Frame 315</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003103-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Tenth: Reel 5, Frame 316</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003104-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Eleventh: Reel 5, Frames 317 and 318</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003106-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003105-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Twelfth: Reel 5, Frames 235 and 236</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003174-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003173-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation><relation type="requires"><description>Thirteenth: Reel 5, Frames 226 and 227</description><extPtr href="images/litmss-003242-0001.jpg" type="simple"/><extPtr href="images/litmss-003241-0001.jpg" type="simple"/></relation></relationships><repository><corpName>Office of Digital Collections and Research</corpName></repository><rights>Baroness Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven's poetry is printed here with the support of the University of Maryland Libraries. Permission to reproduce images of Freytag-Loringhoven's manuscripts has also been generously granted by the libraries.This poem and manuscript drafts are available from this site for demonstration purposes only. Though the intellectual property of Elsa von Freytag-Loringhoven is in the public domain, all annotations and editorial commentary are copyrighted. They may not be reproduced without explicit permission from the copyright holder. For copyright information, please contact Tanya Clement.</rights><description type="summary">The tension between freedom of expression and censorship, between play and structure pervades her work. In particular, it is reflected in the Baroness’s commentary on Germany (which she equated with stultifying restriction) and America (which she associated with dynamic freedom). In 1923, after Little Review stopped publishing her work, the Baroness concluded that she was not appreciated in New York. She wrote to Barnes, “I have not become ‘known enough’ and so I am forgotten,” because “I had fame that kept me admired, jeered at, feared, and poor” (“Selections” 25, 26). As a result— with a loan from William Carlos Williams—Freytag-Loringhoven returned to Germany only to discover that her father had disinherited her. Until 1926, she was despondent, selling newspapers on the street in Berlin until Barnes and others raised enough money to send her to Paris where she subsequently died. In post-war Berlin, the Baroness often reflected on what she looked back on as happier times in the states. Written during this period, the first lines of “Statements/Purgatory Lilt” reflect her opinion of Germany: "GERMANY’S REMAIN IS PERMEATED BY DECAY REEK THROUGHOUT. / EFFECT OF BRAINSTORMING BACKSLIDE—" while the poem concludes with her more hopeful perspective on America, which she has left behind forever. The concluding lines discuss the stifling air (“wheeze I”) the Baroness perceives in the atmosphere of post-war Germany. Germany’s architecture and its “ghosts” or culture is decaying, while in the “sweet soil” of America, she might take root and conceivably flourish. In an undated letter to Djuna Barnes from Germany she writes of her love for America: IT IS ‘LIFE’ THERE—DOING—EVEN IF IN DEFIANCE OF MENTAL POVERTY BENEATH MASK OF GENIUS—FOR THE SAKE OF “MAKING A LIVING.” IT IS PLUCK! IT IS LIFE! THE GERMAN IS NOT EVEN CAPABLE OF IT! HE IS IN TRADITION ROTTEN SCHRUNKEN DIGNITY A DAPPER GRAVE—EXHAUSTED FOOL—WHO DIES OF “CONVICTION” WITHOUT TO KNOW WHAT ABOUT—HE HAS BECOME TOO COMFORTABLY DULL—HAS FORGOTTEN TO MOVE—FIGHT—EXCEPT IN THAT MECHANICAL WAR FASHION WITH WEAPONS (UMD). Reflecting a Dadaist sensibility, the Baroness loves America because she perceives it is a culture not so mired in “dull,” no longer meaningful, traditions like those represented in many “old-world” religions. She perceives that it is a culture of action, a trait she admires. In an another undated letter to Djuna Barnes, the Baroness writes, "COULD YOU NOT BRING THAT -- WHAT I TITLED "HELL'S WISDOM"? IT IS VERY PERSONALYPERSONALLY --AND AGAIN -- NOT - AT - ALL. -- JUST PRECISELY PRINTING OUT WHERE I STAND IN UNIVERSE -- AND WHY -- SO PRECARIOUSLY! DJUNA. BESIDES --IT IS CRISTALL IN STILESTYLE CONCISENESS - INFORMATION ! FOR WEEKS I WORKED ON NOTHING BUT THE STYLE OF THE THING. AND I LOVE THE ARITHMETIC IN IT! TOGETHER WITH YOUR PREFACE -- TRYING TO ARROUSE INTERREST INTEREST FOR ME -- HELP -- SYMPATHY (AND I NEED IT! HEAVEN HELP -- HOW I DO -- IN ORDER TO BE SAVED TO DO MY ART --FOR I CANNOT BE SAVED OTHERWISE OTHERWISE IS BLANKNESS --THAT MEANS NECESSARY DEATH! WITH YOUR GENEROUS PREFACE -- MY OWN DJUNA -- WOULD IT NOT BE WONDERFULLWONDERFULTOGETHER? i WONDER -- YOU DID NOT THINK OF IT. THATN THERE IS THAT: "PURGATORY LILT." PROVING MY DEVOTION TO AMERICA -- AND THE ROTTING -- YOU SEE -- I AM DERANGED -- DJUNA -- TEMPORARELYTEMPORARILY BECAUSE I _KNOW IT_ - AS MY MOTHER DID - WHEN SHE WAS - SHE KNEW SHE WAS NOT CRAZY - _BUT SHE_s ALSO KNEW - SHE WAS ASTRAY - UNCOLLECTED IN MIND. I CANNOT CONCENTRATE TO CREATE --MY MISERY INTRUDES UNSHAPED -- AS BEFORE --PAIN BECAME EXALTED SHAPE! I HAVE START OF MENTAL CANCER -- MUST GO MAD ON BARREN ROCK OF GERMANY GROS AGE STUPIDITY [. . .] (UMD 2.262-263)</description><subject type="browse">Literature, Print Culture</subject></descMeta></str>
